(Music)
(موسيقى)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you very much. (Applause)
شكراً جزيلاً. (تصفيق)
Thank you. It's a distinct privilege to be here.
شكراً. انه لشرف عظيم ان اكون هنا
A few weeks ago, I saw a video on YouTube
قبل بضعة اسابيع رأيت فيديو على اليوتيوب
of Congresswoman Gabrielle Giffords
لعضوة الكونجرس غابرييل جيفوردز
at the early stages of her recovery
في المراحل الأولى من شفائها
from one of those awful bullets.
من واحدة من تلك الرصاصات الفظيعة.
This one entered her left hemisphere, and
هذه دخلت في الجزء الايسر من جمجمتها
knocked out her Broca's area, the speech center of her brain.
واصابت منطقة بروكا، مركز الكلام في الدماغ
And in this session, Gabby's working with a speech therapist,
وفي هذه الجلسة غابي تعمل مع معالج كلام
and she's struggling to produce
وهي تكافح لانتاج
some of the most basic words, and you can see her
بعض ابسط الكلمات الاساسية، ويمكنكم رؤيتها
growing more and more devastated, until she ultimately
تتدمر اكثر واكثر حتى في النهاية
breaks down into sobbing tears, and she starts sobbing
تنهار بالبكاء وتبدأ تنتحب
wordlessly into the arms of her therapist.
بدون كلمات في حضن معالجها
And after a few moments, her therapist tries a new tack,
وبعد عدّة دقائق المعالج يحاول مسلك جديد
and they start singing together,
ويبؤون في الغناء معاً
and Gabby starts to sing through her tears,
و تبدأ غابي الغناء عبر دموعها
and you can hear her clearly able to enunciate
ويمكنكم سماعها بكل وضوح قادرة على نطق
the words to a song that describe the way she feels,
كلمات اغنية تصف ما تشعر به
and she sings, in one descending scale, she sings,
وهي تغني في مقياس تنازلي واحد، تغني
"Let it shine, let it shine, let it shine."
"دعه يتألق، دعه يتألق، دعه يتألق"
And it's a very powerful and poignant reminder of how
وانها تذكرة قوية جدا ومؤثرة لكيفية
the beauty of music has the ability to speak
جمال الموسيقى لديه القدرة على الكلام
where words fail, in this case literally speak.
حيث تعجز الكلمات، في هذه الحالة التحدث حرفيا.
Seeing this video of Gabby Giffords reminded me
رؤية هذا الفيديو لغابي جيفوردز ذكرني
of the work of Dr. Gottfried Schlaug,
بعمل الدكتور غوتفريد شلوغ
one of the preeminent neuroscientists studying music and the brain at Harvard,
واحد من أبرز علماء الأعصاب يقوم بدراسة الموسيقى والدماغ في جامعة هارفارد،
and Schlaug is a proponent of a therapy called
وشلوغ من دعاة علاج يسمى
Melodic Intonation Therapy, which has become very popular in music therapy now.
علاج الترنيم اللحني، والذي أصبح يحظى بشعبية كبيرة في العلاج بالموسيقى الآن.
Schlaug found that his stroke victims who were aphasic,
شلوغ وجد ان مرضاه الذين عانوا من السكتة الدماغية الذين كانوا فقدوا القدرة على الكلام
could not form sentences of three- or four-word sentences,
لم يكن بإمكانهم ان يكونو جملة من ثلاثة او اربعة كلمات
but they could still sing the lyrics to a song,
لكن مازال بإمكانهم ان يغنو كلمات اغنية
whether it was "Happy Birthday To You"
سواء كان "عيد ميلاد سعيد"
or their favorite song by the Eagles or the Rolling Stones.
او اغانيهم المفضلة لذي ايغلز او رولينغ ستونز
And after 70 hours of intensive singing lessons,
وبعد 70 ساعة من دروس الغناء المكثفة
he found that the music was able to literally rewire
وجد ان الموسيقى بامكانها حرفياً اعادة توصيل
the brains of his patients and create a homologous
ادمغة مرضاه و تكوين مركز كلام
speech center in their right hemisphere
مماثل في النصف الايمن
to compensate for the left hemisphere's damage.
لتعويض الضرر في النصف الايسر
When I was 17, I visited Dr. Schlaug's lab, and in one afternoon
عندما كنت في السابعة عشرة زرت مختبر دكتور شلوغ وفي بعد ظهيرة واحدة
he walked me through some of the leading research
شرح لي عن بعض الابحاث الرائدة
on music and the brain -- how musicians had
في الموسيقى والدماغ-- كيف ان الموسيقيين لديهم
fundamentally different brain structure than non-musicians,
بنية دماغ مختلفة اختلاف جوهري عن غير الموسيقيين
how music, and listening to music,
كيف الموسيقى والاستمتاع الى الموسيقى
could just light up the entire brain, from
يمكنها ان تضيء كامل الدماغ
our prefrontal cortex all the way back to our cerebellum,
من قشرة الفص الجبهي لدينا حتى العودة إلى المخيخ،
how music was becoming a neuropsychiatric modality
كيف اصبحت الموسيقى طريقة نفسية عصبية
to help children with autism, to help people struggling
لمساعدة الاطفال المتوحدين، لمساعدة الاشخاص المعانين
with stress and anxiety and depression,
من التوتر والقلق والاكتئاب
how deeply Parkinsonian patients would find that their tremor
مدى عمق اكتشاف مرضى الشلل الرعاشي ان ارتعاشهم
and their gait would steady when they listened to music,
ومشيتهم تصبح ثابتة عند استماعهم للموسيقى
and how late-stage Alzheimer's patients, whose dementia
وكيف ان مرضى المراحل المتاخرة من الزهايمر الذين
was so far progressed that they could no longer recognize
تقدم بهم الخرف الى درجة انه لم يعد بإمكانهم ان يتعرفوا على افراد عائلتهم
their family, could still pick out a tune by Chopin
مازال بامكانهم عزف لحن لتشوبين
at the piano that they had learned when they were children.
على البيانو الذي تعلموه عندما كانو اطفالاً.
But I had an ulterior motive of visiting Gottfried Schlaug,
ولكن كان لدي حافز خفي من زيارة غوتفريد شلوغ،
and it was this: that I was at a crossroads in my life,
وكان ذلك انني كنت في مفترق طرق في حياتي
trying to choose between music and medicine.
محاولاً الاختيار بين الموسيقى والطب
I had just completed my undergraduate, and I was working
كنت قد اكملت مرحلتي الجامعية للتو
as a research assistant at the lab of Dennis Selkoe,
وقد كنت اعمل كمساعد في مختبر دينيس سيلكو
studying Parkinson's disease at Harvard, and I had fallen
ادرس الشلل الرعاشي في هارفارد
in love with neuroscience. I wanted to become a surgeon.
وكنت وقعت في غرام علم الاعصاب واردت ان اصبح جراحاً
I wanted to become a doctor like Paul Farmer or Rick Hodes,
اردت ان اصبح طبيباً مثل باول فارمر او ريك هودز
these kind of fearless men who go into places like Haiti or Ethiopia
هذا النوع من الرجال الشجعان الذين يذهبون لأماكن مثل هاييتي او إثيوبيا
and work with AIDS patients with multidrug-resistant
ويعملون مع مرضى الايدز المقاوم للأدوية المتعددة
tuberculosis, or with children with disfiguring cancers.
او السل، أو مع الأطفال الذين يعانون من تشوهات السرطان.
I wanted to become that kind of Red Cross doctor,
اردت ان اصبح هذا النوع من اطباء الصليب الاحمر
that doctor without borders.
ذلك الطبيب بلا حدود
On the other hand, I had played the violin my entire life.
من ناحية أخرى، كنت قد عزفت على الكمان حياتي كلها.
Music for me was more than a passion. It was obsession.
الموسيقى بالنسبة لي كانت اكثر من شغف، كانت هوس
It was oxygen. I was lucky enough to have studied
كانت اوكسيجين، كنت محظوظا بما فيه الكفاية للدراسة
at the Juilliard School in Manhattan, and to have played
في مدرسة جوليارد في مانهاتن
my debut with Zubin Mehta and the Israeli philharmonic orchestra in Tel Aviv,
واني عزفت أول مشاركة لي مع زوبين ميهتا والأوركسترا الفيلهارمونية الإسرائيلية في تل أبيب،
and it turned out that Gottfried Schlaug
واتضح ان غوتفريد شلوغ
had studied as an organist at the Vienna Conservatory,
درس كعازف اورغن في المعهد الموسيقي في فيينا
but had given up his love for music to pursue a career
لكن تخلى عن حبه للموسيقى لممارسة مهنة الطب
in medicine. And that afternoon, I had to ask him,
وبعد ظهر ذلك اليوم، كان علي أن أسأله،
"How was it for you making that decision?"
"كيف كان اتخاذ ذلك القرار بالنسبة اليك؟"
And he said that there were still times when he wished
وقال انه هناك اوقات تمنى فيها
he could go back and play the organ the way he used to,
لو انه يستطيع العودة والعزف على الاورغن بالطريقة التي اعتادها
and that for me, medical school could wait,
وبالنسبة لي كلية الطب تستطيع ان تنتظر
but that the violin simply would not.
لكن الكمان لا يستطيع ببساطة
And after two more years of studying music, I decided
وبعد سنتين من دراسة الموسيقى، قررت
to shoot for the impossible before taking the MCAT
للتصويب نحو المستحيل قبل أخذ اختبار قبول كلية الطب
and applying to medical school like a good Indian son
والتقديم لكلية الطب كأبن هندي جيد
to become the next Dr. Gupta. (Laughter)
لاصبح د.غوبتا القادم. (ضحك)
And I decided to shoot for the impossible and I took
وقررت التصويب نحو المستحيل وقدمت
an audition for the esteemed Los Angeles Philharmonic.
تجربة اداء لأوركسترا لوس أنجلوس الموقرة.
It was my first audition, and after three days of playing
كانت تجربة ادائي الاولى، وبعد ثلاثة ايام من العزف
behind a screen in a trial week, I was offered the position.
خلف شاشة في اسبوع التجارب، عرض علي مركز
And it was a dream. It was a wild dream to perform
وكان حلم، حلم جامح الأداء في اوركسترا
in an orchestra, to perform in the iconic Walt Disney Concert Hall
الأداء في قاعة والت ديزني الموسيقية الشهيرة
in an orchestra conducted now by the famous Gustavo Dudamel,
في اوركسترا يقودها الآن الموسيقار الشهير غوستاف دوداميل
but much more importantly to me to be surrounded
لكن اهم كثيرا بالنسبة لي ان اكون محاطاً
by musicians and mentors that became my new family,
بموسيقيين ومرشدين الذين أصبحوا عائلتي الجديدة،
my new musical home.
منزلي الموسيقي الجديد
But a year later, I met another musician who had also
لكن بعد سنة التقيت بموسيقي درس ايضاً
studied at Juilliard, one who profoundly helped me
في جوليارد، شخص قام بمساعدتي كثيراً
find my voice and shaped my identity as a musician.
في ايجاد صوتي وتشكيل هويتي كموسيقي
Nathaniel Ayers was a double bassist at Juilliard, but
ناثانيال آيرز كان عازف باص مزدوج في جوليارد
he suffered a series of psychotic episodes in his early 20s,
لكنه تعرض لسلسة من الاضطرابات الذهنية في بداية عشرينياته
was treated with thorazine at Bellevue,
وتمت معالجته بالثورازين في بيفيو
and ended up living homeless on the streets of Skid Row
وانتهى به المطاف مشردا يعيش في شوارع سكيد رو
in downtown Los Angeles 30 years later.
في وسط مدينة لوس انجليس بعد 30 عاما.
Nathaniel's story has become a beacon for homelessness
أصبحت قصة ناثانيل منارة للتشرد
and mental health advocacy throughout the United States,
ومؤيدي الصحة النفسية في جميع أنحاء الولايات المتحدة،
as told through the book and the movie "The Soloist,"
كما ذكر من خلال كتاب وفيلم "العازف المنفرد"
but I became his friend, and I became his violin teacher,
لكني اصبحت صديقه واصبحت معلمه في الكمان
and I told him that wherever he had his violin,
واخبرته انه حيثما كان لديه كمانه
and wherever I had mine, I would play a lesson with him.
وحيثما كان لدي كماني، فاني ساعزف درساً معه
And on the many times I saw Nathaniel on Skid Row,
وفي المرات العديدة التي رأيت فيها ناثانيل في سكيد رو
I witnessed how music was able to bring him back
شهدت كيف ان الموسيقى استطاعت ان تعيده
from his very darkest moments, from what seemed to me
من احلك لحظاته، مما بدى لي
in my untrained eye to be
في عيني غير المدربة
the beginnings of a schizophrenic episode.
بداية انفصام شخصية
Playing for Nathaniel, the music took on a deeper meaning,
العزف بالنسبة لناثانيال، اخذت الموسيقى معنى اعمق
because now it was about communication,
لأنه الان اصبحت عن التواصل
a communication where words failed, a communication
التواصل حيث تفشل الكلمات،
of a message that went deeper than words, that registered
تواصل رسالة وصلت اعمق من الكلمات
at a fundamentally primal level in Nathaniel's psyche,
سجلت على مستوى أساسي في النفس البدائية لناثانيل
yet came as a true musical offering from me.
بالرغم من ذلك جاءت كتقديم موسيقي حقيقي مني
I found myself growing outraged that someone
وجدت نفسي متزايد الغضب أن شخصا
like Nathaniel could have ever been homeless on Skid Row
مثل ناثانيال بإمكانه ان يصبح مشرداً في سكيد رو
because of his mental illness, yet how many tens of thousands
بسبب مرضه العقلي، لكن كم من عشرات الالاف
of others there were out there on Skid Row alone
من الاخرين موجودين في سكيد رو وحدها
who had stories as tragic as his, but were never going to have a book or a movie
لديهم قصص مأساوية كقصته، لكن لن يكون لديهم ابداً كتاب او فلم
made about them that got them off the streets?
يحكي عنهم لأخذهم من الشارع
And at the very core of this crisis of mine, I felt somehow
وفي لب ازمتي هذه، شعرت بطريقة ما
the life of music had chosen me, where somehow,
ان حياة الموسيقى اختارتني، حيث بطريقة ما
perhaps possibly in a very naive sense, I felt what Skid Row
ربما على الارجح في احساس ساذج، شعرت ان
really needed was somebody like Paul Farmer
ما تحتاجه سكيد رو حقاً هو شخص مثل بول فارمر
and not another classical musician playing on Bunker Hill.
وليس موسيقي تقليدي آخر يعزف على بانكر هيل
But in the end, it was Nathaniel who showed me
لكن في النهاية كان ناثانيال هو من اراني
that if I was truly passionate about change,
انني اذا ما كنت حقاً شغوف حول التغيير
if I wanted to make a difference, I already had the perfect instrument to do it,
اذا ما كنت اريد عمل فرق، كانت لدي الآلة المثالية للقيام بذلك
that music was the bridge that connected my world and his.
ان الموسيقى كان الجسر الذي ربط عالمي بعالمه
There's a beautiful quote
هناك اقتباس جميل
by the Romantic German composer Robert Schumann,
من الملحن الرومانسي الالماني روبرت شومان
who said, "To send light into the darkness of men's hearts,
الذي قال:"ارسال الضوء الى ظلام قلوب الرجال،
such is the duty of the artist."
هذا واجب الفنان."
And this is a particularly poignant quote
وهذا اقتباس مؤثر خصوصا
because Schumann himself suffered from schizophrenia
لأن شومان نفسه كان يعاني من انفصام الشخصية
and died in asylum.
ومات في المصحة.
And inspired by what I learned from Nathaniel,
ومستوحى من ما تعلمته من ناثانيل،
I started an organization on Skid Row of musicians
بدأت منظمة في سكيد رو للموسيقيين
called Street Symphony, bringing the light of music
تدعى سيمفونية الشارع، ليصل ضوء الموسيقى
into the very darkest places, performing
الى احلك الاماكن،
for the homeless and mentally ill at shelters and clinics
تعزف للمشردين والمرضي النفسيين في الملاجئ و العيادات
on Skid Row, performing for combat veterans
في سكيد رو، تؤدي لقدامى المحاربين
with post-traumatic stress disorder, and for the incarcerated
مع اضطراب ما بعد الصدمة، وللمسجونين
and those labeled as criminally insane.
واولئك الموسومين بانهم مجانين اجراميا
After one of our events at the Patton State Hospital
بعد واحدة من فعالياتنا في مستشفى ولاية باتون
in San Bernardino, a woman walked up to us
في سانت بيرناردينو، جاءت الينا امراة
and she had tears streaming down her face,
و كان الدموع تجري على خديها
and she had a palsy, she was shaking,
وكان لديها شلل رعاشي، وكانت تهتز
and she had this gorgeous smile, and she said
وكانت لديها ابتسامة خلابة، وقالت
that she had never heard classical music before,
انها لم تسمع موسيقى كلاسيكية من قبل
she didn't think she was going to like it, she had never
لم تظن انها ستعجبها، لم يسبق لها
heard a violin before, but that hearing this music was like hearing the sunshine,
ان سمعت كمان، لكن سماع هذه الموسيقى كان مثل سماع ضوء الشمس
and that nobody ever came to visit them, and that for the first time in six years,
وانه لم ياتي احد لزيارتهم، ولأول مرة في 6 سنوات
when she heard us play, she stopped shaking without medication.
عندما سمعتنا نعزف، توقفت عن الاهتزاز بدون دواء
Suddenly, what we're finding with these concerts,
فجأة ما كنا نجده في هذه الحفلات
away from the stage, away from the footlights, out
بعيداً عن المسرح بعيدا عن أضواء المسرح
of the tuxedo tails, the musicians become the conduit
خارج بذل السهرة، الموسيقيين اصبحو القناة
for delivering the tremendous therapeutic benefits
لتقديم فوائد علاجية هائلة
of music on the brain to an audience that would never
من الموسيقى على الدماغ لجمهور
have access to this room,
لن يكون لديهم وصول لهذه الغرفة
would never have access to the kind of music that we make.
لن يكون لديهم وصول الى النوع من الموسيقى الذي نعزفه
Just as medicine serves to heal more
كما يقدم الدواء للشفاء أكثر
than the building blocks of the body alone,
من قطع بناء الجسم وحده،
the power and beauty of music transcends the "E"
قوة وجمال الموسيقى تسمو فوق "E"
in the middle of our beloved acronym.
في منتصف مقطوعة موسيقية مختصرة
Music transcends the aesthetic beauty alone.
الموسيقى تسمو فوق الجمال الجمالي وحده.
The synchrony of emotions that we experience when we
تزامن من العواطف الذي نعيشه عندما
hear an opera by Wagner, or a symphony by Brahms,
نسمع اوبرا لوانغر او سيمفونية لبراهمز
or chamber music by Beethoven, compels us to remember
أو موسيقى الحجرة لبيتهوفن، تفرض علينا أن نتذكر
our shared, common humanity, the deeply communal
هدفنا المشترك والإنسانية المشتركة، والوعي المجتمعي العميق
connected consciousness, the empathic consciousness
المتصل، الوعي التعاطفي
that neuropsychiatrist Iain McGilchrist says is hard-wired
بحيث يقول عنه طبيب النفس و الأعصاب ايان مكجيلكريست انه
into our brain's right hemisphere.
موجود بالفطرة في النصف الايمن من الدماغ
And for those living in the most dehumanizing conditions
وبالنسبة لأولئك الذين يعيشون في الظروف اللاإنسانية
of mental illness within homelessness
المرض العقلي في غضون التشرد والسجن،
and incarceration, the music and the beauty of music
والموسيقى وجمال الموسيقى
offers a chance for them to transcend the world around them,
يوفر فرصة لهم لتجاوز العالم من حولهم،
to remember that they still have the capacity to experience
لتذكر انهم مازال لديهم القدرة على تجربة
something beautiful and that humanity has not forgotten them.
شيء جميل وان الإنسانية لم تنسهم
And the spark of that beauty, the spark of that humanity
وشرارة ذلك الجمال شرارة تلك الإنسانية
transforms into hope,
تتحول الى امل
and we know, whether we choose the path of music
ونحن نعرف سواء اخترنا مسار الموسيقى
or of medicine, that's the very first thing we must instill
او الطب وهذا هو أول شيء يجب علينا غرسه
within our communities, within our audiences,
في مجتمعاتنا في جمهورنا
if we want to inspire healing from within.
إذا كنا نريد أن يلهم الشفاء من الداخل.
I'd like to end with a quote by John Keats,
ايد ان اختم بإقتباس من جون كيتس
the Romantic English poet,
الشاعر الانجليزي الرومانسي
a very famous quote that I'm sure all of you know.
اقتباس شهير جداً انا متأكد من انكم كلكم تعرفونه
Keats himself had also given up a career in medicine
كيتس نفسه ايضاً تخلى عن مهنة في الطب
to pursue poetry, but he died when he was a year older than me.
للسعي وراء الشعر لكنه توفى عندما كان يكبرني بسنة
And Keats said, "Beauty is truth, and truth beauty.
وكيتس قال:"الجمال هو الحقيقة، والحقيقة جمال.
That is all ye know on Earth, and all ye need to know."
هذا هو كل شيء تعرفه على الأرض، وجميع ما تحتاج إلى معرفته. "
(Music)
(موسيقى)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)